

CONTACT



mary.breenlyles@gmail.com



www.marybreenlyles.com

EDUCATION **S**



M.S. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING Northern Illinois University

August 2019 (GPA 3.9)

B.S. PHYSICS

Beloit College

May 2017 (GPA 3.9)

Course work in Data Structures and Algorithms / OO Programming

HONORS



Co-author of ASME Publication (2017)

Performance of Supercharged Engine Fueled with CTI Binary Mixture at Dierent Injection Pressures

Walter S. Haven Physics Prize (2017)

Granted in honor of excellent work with the Physics Department's accelerator.

Departmental Honors (awarded May 2017) Awarded by Physics Dept of Beloit College

Phi Beta Kappa Member (inducted May 2017)

Oldest and one of the most prestigious academic honor societies in the US

Presidential Scholarship (2014-2017)

Beloit College's prestigious honor awarded for exceptional academic achievement.

Dean's List (2014-2017)

SKILLS



VS Code MATLAB
Eclipse Java
Adobe Illustrator Python
Postman Unix / Linux

ElasticSearch Tcl

Redis HTML, CSS, JS

Consuming REST APIs Git
Regular Expressions Celery
Project Estimation jQuery
Client Communication PHP

Mary Elizabeth Breen-Lyles

PROGRAMMER - ENGINEER - RESEARCHER

SUMMARY

Fast-learning, methodical worker with 2 years development experience and significant coding/software experience from a diverse set of engineering and research applications in both academic and professional settings. Maintains a strong mathematical aptitude and a passion for problem-solving. Lover of people and sincere communication, and always a tenacious team member with a genuine enthusiasm for learning and improvement.

RECENT PROJECTS

Extensible Amazon Web Scraper (2020)

- Built a modular, well-documented web scraper for harvesting Amazon product data at managed intervals, storing data and comprehensive logs in ElasticSearch, utilizing Celery with Redis for parallel processing and data buffering
- ▶ Python, Selenium, Redis (in-memory DB, queue), Celery (asynchronous tasks), ELK stack, Pipenv, Github

Vendor Velocity Free Tools (2019)

- Created 2 front end web tools leveraging Amazon's Product Advertising API that Amazon vendors can use to improve their marketing strategies.
- ▶ PHP, Javascript, CSS, HTML, jQuery, PipEnv, GitHub. Utilized jsGrid to neatly display data to the user.

WORK EXPERIENCE

2019

Freelance Web Developer, Self

Chicago, IL (July 2019 - present)

- ► Communicate effectively and harmoniously to maintain positive client relationships
- ► Draw up thorough contract documents with detailed descriptions for project plans/estimates
- Independently build web tools and applications for multiple clients while managing both business and technical aspects of the projects, always delivering high-quality production code

2018

Graduate Research Assistant, Northern Illinois University

DeKalb, IL (January 2018 - August 2019)

- Designed/executed molecular simulations across distributed systems to demonstrate effectiveness of polymer grafting at enhancing mechanical properties of a cellulose nanofiller
- Worked with Tcl Scripting and Python for data analysis, and used MAKE to compile LAMMPS from C++ source code
- ► Utilized Unix/ Linux as both my development and runtime environment. Interacted extensively with a remote Linux HPC cluster

2017

Research Assistant, Beloit College

Beloit, WI (August 2016 - May 2017)

- ► Repaired proton accelerator via machining and configurational planning for new/existing instrumentation
- Extensive work on electromagnet (cooling system, Faraday cup implementation, electrical load and bending angle calculations)
- ► Tuned magnet based on initial predictions and later testing. Used MATLAB, thermal imaging, and thermocouple, voltmeter, ammeter data for analysis

2016

Undergraduate Research Fellow, Georgia Southern University

Statesboro, GA (June 2016 - August 2016)

- ► Wrote programs in LabVIEW to pass data from sensors on a diesel engine to computers
- Developed LabVIEW programs for pressure transducers, accelerometers, and flow meters on a jet turbine engine
- Gained experience in sensor calibration, instrumentation, advanced data acquisition and programming

2015

Sustainability Fellow, Beloit College

Beloit, WI (September 2015 - May 2016)

- ► Wrote program to compute thermodynamic properties of new campus building
- Developed rigorous model using thermal FEA to predict HVAC needs
- Presented at 2016 Student Symposium and to Beloit College Board of Trustees